This video is brought to you by
Brilliant. Click the link in the
description to take advantage of a
special offer for Arvin Ash viewers.
Energy cannot be created or destroyed.
When you kick a soccer ball, the energy
you expend in moving your foot is
transferred to the movement or kinetic
energy of the soccer ball. Some of this
energy is also expended in the form of
heat and sound. But if you were to add
up all the energy from the start to
finish, you would find that the total
energy did not change. This rule applies
to everything. No matter how you
transfer or transform energy, kicking a
soccer ball, driving a car, lighting a
candle, the total amount of energy stays
constant overall. The same goes for
momentum. When objects collide, their
momentum just gets passed around. These
are examples of conservation laws in
physics, and they're probably the most
fundamental principles we know of. But
what's even more fascinating is why
these laws hold true. Turns out that
each conservation law is tied to a deep
symmetry in nature. This connection was
first uncovered by mathematician Emmy
Neiter and it's one of the most
beautiful ideas in physics. If nature's
laws have a certain symmetry, then
something will be conserved always. In
this video, I'll break down the three
major conservation laws and show you why
and how they reveal a fundamental
symmetry in the universe and how Niter's
genius helped uncover some of the
deepest secrets of reality. You don't
want to miss this because that's coming
up right now.
[Music]
Let's start with the three major
conservation laws. These are the VIPs of
physics that never break as long as
nothing from the outside interferes. The
first is conservation of energy. Energy
cannot be created out of nothing nor
destroyed to nothingness. It can only
change form. For example, chemical
energy in fuel turns into kinetic energy
of a car which turns into heat and so
on. But if you add it all up, the total
energy stays the same. This rule, the
first law of thermodynamics is
absolutely fundamental. The second is
conservation of momentum. There's linear
and angular. Both are important, but for
simplicity, I'll talk about linear
momentum. Just know that the same
principle applies to the total spin of a
system. Momentum is the product of mass
times velocity. You can think of it as
how much something is moving. Heavier
things moving faster have more momentum
than lighter things moving slower. In an
isolated system, the total momentum
remains constant. When playing
billiards, for example, when the Q ball
hits object balls, its momentum is
transferred. If you added up the mass
times velocity of all the balls before
and after the collision, it would remain
the same. The third is conservation of
electric charge. The total charge of a
system remains the same. Charge can be
transferred but not created or
destroyed. So for example in a chemical
reaction when one molecule gains a
negative charge due to the transfer of
an electron the other molecule gains a
positive charge. Total charge remains
the same in an isolated system. You
can't create charge out of nothing.
These are the big ones energy momentum
and charge. There are other conservation
laws like conservation of leptton number
or berion number in particle physics or
the combined conservation of mass energy
which merges mass and energy together.
But the three above are considered the
bedrock conservation laws that apply
across a huge range of physical
phenomena. They were discovered by
observing that nothing ever seemed to
violate them. No one ever saw energy
just pop into existence or disappear.
For example, for a long time they were
just how nature works. But that wasn't a
fully satisfying answer. It felt like
there must be a reason why these
quantities are the ones that nature
chooses to keep constant. And that's
where symmetry enters the story. What is
the meaning of symmetry? When we hear
symmetry, we think of visual patterns
like a butterfly with matching left and
right wings, a perfectly round
snowflake, or letters like H and O that
look the same in a mirror.
In everyday language, symmetry means a
change that leaves something looking the
same. If you rotate a snowflake, it
lines up with itself again. That's
rotational symmetry. In physics, we
extend this idea to the laws of nature.
A symmetry means that when you make a
change or transformation in a system,
the governing laws or equations do not
change. It's an invariance. For example,
imagine you perform an experiment today
and then the exact same experiment
tomorrow. If the laws of physics are
time symmetric, the results should be
identical. That is the underlying rules
don't care when you do the experiment.
This is a symmetry in time or time
translation symmetry. Likewise, if you
do an experiment in New York City and
then do the same thing in Beijing, you
will get the same outcome if conditions
are the same. This tells us that the
laws of physics are symmetric in space.
They don't care where you are. No
particular location in the universe has
special physics. That's spatial or space
translation symmetry. Just like a mirror
image or rotated shape can be invariant
in appearance, a physical process can be
invariant in its outcomes under a shift
in time or space. Physicists and
mathematicians say the system is
invariant under that transformation.
But here's the key insight that was
proven by Emmy Noer around 1918.
Whenever you have such a symmetry,
something must be conserved. It's now
called Niter's theorem. Stated
informally, the theorem says for every
continuous symmetry of a physical
system, there's a corresponding
conserved quantity. So, what properties
are conserved with time and space
translation symmetry? Time translation
symmetry leads to conservation of energy
and space translation symmetry leads to
conservation of momentum. Similarly,
something called gauge symmetry leads to
conservation of electric charge. This is
a more complicated concept, but I will
add this as a bonus at the end of the
video if you really want to dive into
the nitty-gritty of quantum physics. Let
me first address the question I posed in
the title of this video by thoroughly
explaining how time translation symmetry
leads to energy conservation. Then I'll
explain the other two conserved
quantities. First, you should know that
energy is a kind of currency in the
universe. It can make things move, heat
things up, create light, or even hold
things together. Energy can switch forms
from motion to heat, like the brakes in
your car, from electricity to sound like
the speakers in your headphones. But it
can't disappear or appear out of
nowhere. But imagine if this was not the
case. Imagine what it would mean if
energy was not conserved. If energy
suddenly appeared out of nowhere, it
would mean there was a special moment in
time when extra energy was created,
breaking the idea that the rules of the
universe are constant over time. If
energy suddenly disappeared, again,
there would be a special moment in time
where the rules changed. In other words,
changing energy would mean the universe
has special moments where the rules
shift, making things different today
than yesterday. But since we see that
the universe's rules don't change from
moment to moment, that is we have time
symmetry, the universe can't have these
special moments when energy is suddenly
appears or disappears. In other words,
if the rules stay the same, the universe
has no way to choose or suddenly find a
special moment in time to add or remove
energy. If energy appeared or
disappeared, that would mean the
universe was different at one moment
compared to another. But because the
universe is symmetrical in time, energy
must remain constant to keep the
symmetry true. Emmy Noer proved this
mathematically that time symmetry leads
directly to the universe conserving
energy. Now I'm going to address the
other two conserved quantities and how
they lead to conservation of momentum
and electric charge. As I said earlier,
space translation symmetry means that
the laws of physics are the same in New
York as they are in Beijing, as they are
in your house. They're the same in the
Milky Way galaxy as they are in the
Andromeda galaxy. For illustration,
let's use an example of two people in a
boat on still waters. If one throws a
basketball to the other, what happens?
The momentum of the basketball is
transferred to the movement of the two
boats. They both move away from each
other. If we did calculations, we would
find that the total momentum of the
basketball was transferred to the boats.
There is some friction of the water in
the real world, which we're going to
ignore for simplicity. But imagine if
this were not the case. What if momentum
was not conserved? What if suddenly the
momentum changed for no reason? Like one
of the boats started moving with no push
of any kind. This would mean that
something changed in the laws of the
universe depending on where the boats
are located in the water. But space
translation symmetry says that the rules
can't depend on your position. The rules
are the same whether you are here or 3 m
away. In other words, if momentum were
not conserved, it would break the space
translation symmetry. It would imply
that there's a special place in the
universe where momentum can appear or go
away. But translation symmetry forbids
this. Therefore, momentum must stay
constant. Very similarly, rotational
symmetry leads to conservation of
angular momentum as well. Now, let's
look at gauge symmetry leading to the
conservation of charge. This one is a
bit more abstract. So, I'll start with a
simple analogy and then we'll go deeper.
What's your height? Let's say you tell
me that you are 5' 8 in tall. What is
the zero height? Are you measuring this
height from the floor of your house? Are
you measuring it from sea level? Or are
you measuring it from the center of the
earth? If you measure your height from
the floor of your house, it would be a
different number than if you measured it
from sea level. And much different than
the number from the center of the earth.
But changing the place you call zero
height doesn't actually change how tall
you really are, does it? You just chose
a different reference for what you
called zero height. This choice of
starting point is what scientists call
gauge choice. Let's take this analogy
into the physics of electricity. In
electricity, instead of height, we
measure something called potential. It's
kind of like the electric height for
charges. Charges move from higher
electric potential to lower ones, just
like water flows downhill. But just like
the height example, the place you choose
as zero electric potential is up to you.
You can choose any reference point you
want. You could choose the negative side
of a battery as zero or you could choose
the positive side of a battery as zero.
When you change the zero point, the
number for potential will be shifted
everywhere in the universe. But even
though the numbers have changed, the
behavior of charges and electricity will
remain exactly the same. This
flexibility to choose the zero point for
electric potential without affecting
real physics is what we call gauge
symmetry. Now, how does this freedom to
choose your reference, the gauge
symmetry, lead to electric charge
conservation? Here's how. Gauge symmetry
says you can shift your potential, your
zero point, however you want, and
nothing physically real changes. If this
were not the case, it would mean that
electric charge could just appear or
vanish randomly and the electric field
patterns would change unpredictably.
That means suddenly your choice of zero
point would matter. It would affect
reality breaking gauge symmetry. But
gauge symmetry is fundamental. It's
built into how electric and magnetic
fields work. Nature never breaks this
symmetry.
So electric charges can't simply appear
or disappear randomly. The total amount
must always remain constant and this is
called conservation of charge. In other
words, gauge symmetry forces charges to
behave in a consistent predictable way,
never popping in or out of existence.
Charges can move around, but the
universe's total charge stays constant.
Your choice of zero point for potential
doesn't change real physical events. In
each of these cases, Niter's theorem
elevates what once were just observed
facts to something deeper, a logical
consequence of symmetry. Before Niter,
conservation laws were kind of
mysterious random principles confirmed
by experiments but never explained.
After Noer, we understand that they are
demanded by certain symmetries. So, we
can understand where they come from at a
fundamental level. No wonder Einstein
praised her as the most significant
creative mathematical genius. And if you
want to be a mathematical genius, too, a
great start to your journey would be at
brilliant.org, our sponsor today, where
they have a wonderful learning path
called Foundational Math. I love the
Brilliant app because it builds the
foundation in math and science through
hands-on problem solving, then guides
learners through increasingly
challenging, in-depth problems to reach
real learning goals. This method works
best for me, but it's also proven to be
six times more effective than watching
lectures. You'll develop an intuition
for math through visual, interactive,
hands-on problem solving. You'll learn
to think like a mathematician or maybe
even an engineer like me. But Brilliant
will also help you become a better
thinker and problem solver with
thousands of visual interactive lessons
in not only math, but also science,
programming, data analysis, and AI. Goal
oriented learning will be right at your
fingertips. whether at home or on the
go. To learn for free on Brilliant, go
to brilliant.org/arvinash,
scan the QR code on screen or click the
link in the description. Brilliant also
has given our viewers 20% off an annual
premium subscription, which gives you
unlimited daily access to everything on
Brilliant. I encourage you to give it a
try. And if you love the subject of
quantum fields, here is one of our most
popular videos that explains it in
simple terms. I'll see you in the next
video, my friend.
[Music]